<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the publique fast the tenth day of May 1644. at St Maries Oxford, before the Members of the Honourable House of Commons there assembled. / By R. Chalfont B.D. and Fellow of Lincolne Coll. Printed by their order.</title>
            <author>Chalfont, R. (Richard), 1607 or 8-1648.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 101 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78515</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1793</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E9_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15424</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859860</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859860</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111960</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78515)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111960)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 2:E9[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the publique fast the tenth day of May 1644. at St Maries Oxford, before the Members of the Honourable House of Commons there assembled. / By R. Chalfont B.D. and Fellow of Lincolne Coll. Printed by their order.</title>
                  <author>Chalfont, R. (Richard), 1607 or 8-1648.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 42 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henry Hall fo[r] H. Curteyne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: A fast sermon preached in Oxford.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Sept: 23".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Jeremiah XLIV, 10 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111960:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at the PUBLIQUE FAST the tenth day of <hi>May</hi> 1644. at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Maries</hi> OXFORD, <hi>BEFORE</hi> The Members of the Honourable Houſe of COMMONS There Aſſembled.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> R. CHALFONT <hi>B. D.</hi> and Fellow of <hi>Lincolne Coll.</hi> Printed by their Order.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ZEPH 37.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>I ſaid, ſurely thou wilt feare me, thou wilt receive inſtruction, ſo their dwellings ſhould not be cut off, howſoever I p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>niſhed them, but they roſe early, and corrupted all their doings.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by <hi>Henry Hall</hi> to <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 1644.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:111960:2"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Martis 21. Maii 1644.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>By the Committee of COMMONS reſident during the Receſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ORdered that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Conſtantine</hi> give thanks to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Chalfont</hi> for his Sermon Preached at Saint <hi>Maries</hi> the laſt Faſt: and that he deſire him to cauſe the ſame to be printed for the publique good.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Noah Bridges.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111960:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JER. 44.10.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>They are not humbled even unto this day—</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T the very reading of theſe words, the paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel is ſo obvious, me thinks I heare many ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the queſtion with a little change which the <hi>Eunuch</hi> once did of <hi>Philip Act.</hi> 8.34. <hi>Of whom ſpeaketh the Prophet this?</hi> of <hi>us,</hi> or of ſome <hi>other People?</hi> The truth is, in the letter and hiſtorie it is ſpoken of the Jewes, but ſo Symbolically of us of this nation, that your owne thoughts would apply them, ſhould I hold my peace.</p>
            <p>This whole Chapter may be intitled <hi>Noviſsima Jeremiae, Jeremies farewell Sermon to the Jewes.</hi> For if we marke the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall ſtory, it is the laſt extant, and (if the conjecture of ſome be good) his laſt too, that for which well nigh after 45 yeares preaching amongſt them, he was ſtoned to death by the People. In it we have juſt matter to raiſe both our attention &amp; wonder, and that whether we reſpect the <hi>Prophet,</hi> or the <hi>People;</hi> indeed there is nothing of this <hi>Prophet</hi> but 'tis wonderfull, his <hi>Calling,</hi> ordained to be a <hi>Prophet</hi> before he was borne; his <hi>ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 1.5.</note> he was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Peluſiot</hi> calls him, never man tooke more paines with, deſerved better of, and was worſe uſ'd by a people; in this a lively type of him whoſe name was <hi>wonderfull, Vir dolorum,</hi> that ſuffered great contradiction at the hand of ſinners: but above all the <hi>invincibleneſſe of his ſpirit,</hi> his
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:111960:3"/>Heroick Zeale and conſtancie in the Cauſe of <hi>God</hi> and for the good of the <hi>People,</hi> greater then to be diſcouraged by the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of men, or the extremity of miſery. He had now ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viv'd the Funeralls of the <hi>Temple of God,</hi> and his owne <hi>Country,</hi> and liv'd to make the ſad <hi>Elegie</hi> upon the deſolations of both, and after all this was carried away by the violence of a Rebell multitude into a ſtrange accurſed land: Calamities that might have allayed, if not quite quencht the ſpirit of any but <hi>Ieremiah:</hi> but ſuch a ſpirit as his knows not to be diſcouraged, an expreſſe character whereof he hath given us in this Chapter.</p>
            <p>But yet the wonder is far greater, if we looke upon the <hi>People,</hi> whoſe eares if any thing might have <hi>opened to diſcipline</hi> (as <hi>Elihu</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>Iob</hi> 36.10.) and made them ſenſible of their ſinnes, they were written in letters of bloud, they might have read them in the ruines of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> Here the Prophet hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing opened his Commiſſion,<note place="margin">verſ. 2.</note> takes his firſt riſe. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, the God of Iſrael; Ye have ſeene all the evill that I have brought upon Ieruſalem, and upon all the Cities of Iudah, and behold this day they are a deſolation, and no man dwelleth therein, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of their wickedneſſe</hi>—<hi>though I ſent all my ſervants the Prophets riſeing earely and ſending them, ſaying, Oh do not this abhominable thing that I hate, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To ſinne after ſo <hi>Solemne Interdiction,</hi> and warning to the contrary by the concurrent voice of ſo many Ambaſſadors, <hi>All the Prophets</hi> ſent from God to that purpoſe, and thoſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chargeing their duty with ſo much Zeale and ſollicitude; had left them without excuſe. To ſinne after the example of ſo terrible a judgement as that upon <hi>Iudah,</hi> the Hiſtory whereof ſtands like the carkaſſes of Ships that have ſuffered wracke at Sea, to forwarne all paſſengers of the danger of thoſe Sands, at which they were caſt away, or like that Inſcription upon the <hi>Tombe</hi> of <hi>Senacherib,</hi> ſlaine by his owne ſonnes in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of his God, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Oh all ye that paſſe by
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:111960:3"/>looke upon me and be holy.</hi> All ye that heare, and read of my cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, be affraid, &amp; tremble, &amp; do <hi>no more preſumptuouſly:</hi> I ſay, to ſin after the warning of ſuch an <hi>example,</hi> addes a higher gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation to ſinne. There's no man, whoſe head is not of braſſe and his heart of Adamant, that can reade the Tragoedy of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> with drie eies. <hi>Nazianzen</hi> tells us of himſelfe,<note place="margin">Ora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 12.</note> that he never tooke the booke of the <hi>Lamentations</hi> into his hand (and yet this, ſaith he, I do often) but his heart was even quite o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome with ſymphathy and his eyes with teares, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and he againe lamented over the <hi>Lamentations</hi> of <hi>Ieremy.</hi> But to perſevere in the ſame ſinnes after this <hi>Vidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis</hi> their owne <hi>ſight</hi> and <hi>feeling</hi> of thoſe wofull expreſſions of Gods wrath, when the <hi>eye</hi> ſhould have affected the <hi>heart,</hi> and left the laſting impreſſions of feare upon the ſoule; to commit the ſame abhominations ſtill, which had provoked divine vengeance, to the utter deſtruction of their owne Country, while themſelves bare the viſible Characters of Gods fury u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them, this indeed ſets their impiety, their Rebellion <hi>in praecipiti,</hi> upon the very <hi>Pinnacle and top</hi> of ſinne. Here the Prophet mounts his <hi>Battery,</hi> if poſſibly he may make a breach upon their ſtony hearts and at laſt force them to repentance. <hi>Therefore now ſaith the Lord the God of Hoſts the God of Iſrael.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Wherefore commit you this great evill againſt your owne ſoules to cut off from you man and woman, child and ſuckling out of Iudah, to let none remaine? In that ye provoke me unto wrath with the workes of your hands in the land of Egypt, whither ye are gone downe to dwell, that ye might cut your ſelves off and that ye might be a curſe and a reproach among all the Nations of the earth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore <hi>Now ſaith the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Now</hi> after all the demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations of mine indignation againſt you, in ſuch Judgements as were never the like, <hi>Wherefore commit You,</hi> this great evill? <hi>You</hi> that are the poore remnant of thoſe ſo many thouſands of of <hi>Iudah,</hi> as it were a Firebrand ſnatcht out of the Funerall Pile of that once flouriſhing Country, and reprived from the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111960:4"/>Ruines of your Nation; whom I would have preſerv'd for my names ſake, unwilling to extinguiſh and quite cancell the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and the name of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> had you conſulted your owne ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie under my protection: Wherefore doe you by your obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy provoke my Juſtice to your owne deſtruction? Why will you periſh whom I would preſerve? Have you no remorſe towards your owne <hi>ſoules?</hi> are ye willing your <hi>ſoules</hi> ſhould periſh eternally? Have you no pity upon your <hi>Wives?</hi> or if you and they, as much united in guilt as Conjugall Contract, will dye together in the ſame ſinnes, have ye no compaſſion upon your poore Infants, thoſe innocent <hi>ſucklings</hi> that have not as yet contracted the guilt of your Rebellion? Are ye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent there ſhould remaine no other remembrance of <hi>Iudah</hi> but onely of your ſinnes and my wrath? would ye willingly ſtand as an eternall monument to the whole world of divine Fury, <hi>a reproach and a Curſe:</hi> So that poſterity ſhall make mention of your name onely in their ſolemne Execrations, <hi>The Lord make thee a Curſe, and an aſtoniſhment, as he did Ieruſalem and Iudah?</hi> Or what doe you flatter your ſelves with hopes of impunity in <hi>Egypt?</hi> doe you thinke to find ſecurity in that place, whither you have carried downe with you my <hi>Curſe,</hi> and your <hi>old ſins?</hi> is <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> deſtroyed, and ſhall <hi>Egypt</hi> goe free? Have all my Judgements upon you beene like the beating of the aire by the wings of a bird in his flight, that leaves no footſteps or remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance behind him? <hi>Have ye forgotten the wickedneſſe of your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and of your Kings?</hi> Have your Fathers, nay your Kings, been made to drinke deepe of the cup of my Fury, and ſhall you eſcape, who were kept alive onely becauſe ye were the <hi>pooreſt of the people?</hi> Cannot all the Calamities you have ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red bring you upon your knees, and melt your hearts into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition for your ſinnes? I ſhould have thought that the long tract of time and the ſevere diſcipline I have uſed, might long e're this day have led you quite home to repentance. But alas! what ſhall I ſay of you? you have not even to this day ſo much
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:111960:4"/>as ſet one foot in the way thither. <hi>Nondum humiliati,</hi> all the Judgements you have ſuffered, have not made any, no nor the leaſt impreſſion upon you; <hi>God</hi> himſelfe ſeemes amaz'd at this, and to be at a ſtand, as well as the <hi>Prophet,</hi> and to want an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion to reach the height of this obſtinacy, and therefore breakes off in an admiration at the deſperate perverſeneſſe of this People by way of <hi>Epiphonema</hi> in the words of the Text, <hi>They are not humbled even unto this day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe words are <hi>Onus Iudae in terrâ Aegypti. The Burden</hi> of thoſe Jewes, who contrary to Gods <hi>prohibition,</hi> and their own <hi>proteſtation,</hi> were gone downe into <hi>Egypt.</hi> In them you may pleaſe to obſerve with me theſe three particulars. 1. A duty implied, the performance whereof the great Judgements of God ſo long upon them call'd for all their hands, and the want whereof he here upbraides to them by way of admiration, and that is <hi>Humiliation,</hi> they ſhould have beene <hi>humbled.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. The neglect of that duty cenſured, <hi>They are not humbled.</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. The Aggravation of that neglect; 1. from the perſons guilty <hi>They</hi> the Jewes, Gods owne people, that could not pretend Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of their duty, nor of the equity thereof. 2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. From the Circumſtance of time, <hi>even unto this day.</hi> Time they had and teaching enough to have learn'd their duty: but yet after all inſtructions and invitations thereunto by the tenders of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, all comminations againſt them for their obſtinacy; yea moreover and not onely after ſome ſcatterings of wrath upon themſelves in leſſer Judgements, but alſo after as dreadfull a Tempeſt of vengeance as ever fell upon a people; <hi>Even unto this day. They are not humbled even unto this day.</hi> Theſe are the parts of the Text, the ſenſe whereof may be reſolved into theſe three propoſitions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the duty implied, that which this people ought <hi>de jure</hi> to have done when Gods hand was againſt them in thoſe terrible Judgements, the Inference is.</p>
            <p>That when Gods wrath is revealed from heaven againſt a<note place="margin">1 Propoſ.</note>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:111960:5"/>people, in the way of his Judgements, it is high time then for them to be humbled.</p>
            <p n="2">2ly. From the neglect of this duty, in that the Jewes <hi>de facto</hi> in their greateſt diſtreſſe, under the ſoreſt Judgements, were not humbled, I conclude,</p>
            <p>That a people in outward Covenant with God,<note place="margin">2 Prop.</note> may even under the extremity of the greateſt Judgements remaine un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humbled.</p>
            <p n="3">3ly. From the aggravation of this neglect, both in reſpect of the guilt it laies upon ſuch a people in this verſe, and the wrath it drawes downe upon them at the next, The Reſult is,<note place="margin">3. Propoſ.</note>
            </p>
            <p>That it is the higheſt aggravation of the ſinne of a people, &amp; an evident token they are deſigned to ruine, not to be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled under the mighty hand, the great and continued judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God. <hi>They are not humbled even unto this day, neither have they feared nor walked in my Law, nor in my Statutes that I ſet before you and before your Fathers, therefore thus ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, the God of Iſrael, Behold I will ſet my face againſt you for evill, and to cut off all Iudah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſhould I inſiſt upon all theſe propoſitions ſeverally, I feare I ſhould graſpe more matter, then I ſhould be able to hold within the compaſſe of the time; ſhould I omit any, I might ſeeme to treſpaſſe upon the Text. I ſhall therefore take a middle way to reconcile both, pitching upon the firſt as the head ſtreame, the other two as the leſſer into which it runnes, that, as bearing the inſcription of this dayes duty, for the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinall part of this dayes exerciſe; the other two will fall in, either by way of proofe, or Application</p>
            <p>In the handling of which, I ſhall indeavour to follow S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Hieroms</hi> counſell to <hi>Nepotian, Ita docere, ut non clamor populi, ſed gemitus ſuſcitetur;</hi> ſo to ſpeake as to provoke the <hi>teares,</hi> not the <hi>applauſe</hi> of my hearers; ſuch thoughts are unworthy to aſcend this mount at any time, much leſſe at this; words conceived on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the <hi>brain</hi> and born in the <hi>lips</hi> of the Speaker, for the moſ
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111960:5"/>part dye upon the <hi>eare</hi> of the hearer; they which come from the <hi>heart</hi> are likelieſt to deſcend thither; To feaſt the <hi>eare</hi> by an eloquent diſcourſe this day, were to breake the <hi>Faſt</hi> while we are at the Church. The <hi>eare</hi> and the <hi>eye,</hi> every <hi>member</hi> of the body, and faculty of the ſoule, muſt beare a part in this dayes affliction, as well as the <hi>belly:</hi> The <hi>golden eareings</hi> were the matter of which the <hi>golden Calfe</hi> was made, 'twere an abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination to bring them into the houſe of <hi>mourning.</hi> The chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in the day of Gods diſpleaſure and their ſorrow <hi>Exod.</hi> 35.5. were commanded <hi>to plucke off their Ornaments, that God might know what to do unto them,</hi> till then they were not ſo much as in a poſture for mercy; <hi>ſackcloth</hi> and <hi>aſhes</hi> are the beſt Ornaments, <hi>ſighes and teares</hi> the beſt Orators of this day; could I but mourne out a Sermon, and you ſit before the Lord this day weeping, it would be beſt preacht and heard; the word ſowne in teares would be reapt in joy; then might we hope that this <hi>Faſt</hi> would prove a bleſſed <hi>Eve</hi> to ſome glorious <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtivall;</hi> the diſmall cloud of wrath that now darkens the whole land, and almoſt every day falls downe in ſtormes of bloud, would blow over, and the ſunne of Gods favour, which is now hidden, ſhine forth; that we (which the Lord in mercy grant) and this whole Nation might ſee the ſalvation of our God. I come now to the point.</p>
            <p>When Gods wrath is revealed from heaven againſt a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the way of his judgements, then 'tis high time for them to be humbled.</p>
            <p>For the carrying on of which point, I ſhall propound and endeavour to reſolve theſe 3 Queſtions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. What it is to be humbled, and conſequently, what the ſin is of which the Jewes ſtand charged in the Text, <hi>they are not humbled?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. Why 'tis ſaid that when Gods Judgements are upon a people, then 'tis high time for them to be humbled? Theſe 2 <hi>in Theſi.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:111960:6"/>
            <p>And 3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> 
               <hi>In Hypotheſi,</hi> to put our owne Caſe, what cauſe we of this Nation have to be humbled at this day? Having diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patcht theſe, I ſhall then, by Gods grace, cloſe up all with a ſeaſonable application.</p>
            <p>For the firſt what it is to be humbled?</p>
            <p>I anſwere that it is not to be underſtood paſſively, in this ſenſe never Nation more humbled, then <hi>they</hi> in the Text, they were <hi>humiliati à Deo;</hi> a people formerly exalted in Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour above all other in the world, indeed they were his only by way of eminency and diſtinction, <hi>His people;</hi> but now not only degraded from that dignity, but expoſ'd as the greateſt object of contempt and wonder. <hi>How hath the Lord covered the Daughter of Zion with a cloud in his anger, and caſt downe from heaven unto the earth the beauty of Iſrael, and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred not his footſtoole in the day of his anger! Lam.</hi> 2.1. All the Chronicles in the world cannot match the ſad downefall of this People. <hi>Peceatum humiliaverat,</hi> ſinne had <hi>taken</hi> off their <hi>Crowne</hi> from their <hi>heades</hi> and deprived them of their <hi>exellency</hi> they were <hi>humiliati,</hi> but not <hi>humiles, ipſi ſe non humiliaverunt</hi> they did not humble themſelves, 'tis an active humiliation the neglect whereof is upbraided here unto them, and of which God and the Prophet complaine, <hi>They are not humbled even unto this day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This active humiliation, or ſelfe humbling, implies 3 things, 1. A ſenſe both of ſinne and the puniſhment, a tenderneſſe of heart oppoſ'd to that the Greekes call <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullians</hi> language <hi>Duricordia,</hi> the hardneſſe and unmalleable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart, uncapable of any horror of ſinne or impreſſions of wrath, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <hi>indolentia,</hi> ſtupidity, and deſperate ſenſeleſſeneſſe of our hand againſt God, and his againſt us, when though the fierce wrath of God lies upon us, yet we feele it not,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> a <hi>deſpiſing of Chaſtiſement,</hi> a not <hi>laying to heart</hi> of our owne wayes and of Gods, our ſinnes and his judgements, a ſtupidity frequently charg'd againſt this people; one place only
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111960:6"/>I ſhall mention, it comes home to our preſent caſe, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 42.24, 25. <hi>Who gave</hi> Iacob <hi>to the ſpoile, and</hi> Iſrael <hi>to the Robbers? did not the Lord? he againſt whom we have ſinned? for they would not walke in his wayes, neither were they obedient unto his Law. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he hath poured upon him the fury of his anger and the ſtrength of battell: and he hath ſet him on fire round about, yet he knew not: and it burned him, yet he laid it not to heart.</hi> Here is a perfect and full Character of an unhumbled people, to lye under the guilt of the greateſt ſins, and the preſſure of the ſoreſt Judgments, and yet to remaine inſenſible of either, not to lay them to heart.</p>
            <p n="2">2ly. Contrition, <hi>Tremelius</hi> and ſome others render it <hi>nondum attriti,</hi> and upon our owne Margent, according to the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> à radice <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> contrivit, comminu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> we have <hi>contrite</hi> for <hi>humbled</hi> in the Text, <hi>They are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite even unto this day.</hi> The heart is then humbled when it is broken in peices, hence thoſe two phraſes are joined together in Scripture, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Sacrifices of God are a broken ſpirit, a contrite and broken heart</hi> [cor contritum &amp; humiliatum] <hi>O Lord thou wilt not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe.</hi> It is called an abhorring of our ſelves in duſt and aſhes, in <hi>Iob's</hi> phraſe; a rending of the heart, in <hi>Ioeumll's;</hi> a being in bitterneſſe, in <hi>Zecharie's;</hi> Afflicting of the ſoule, in <hi>Moſes;</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of face, in <hi>Daniel's;</hi> a laying of the mouth in the duſt, in <hi>Ieremie's;</hi> it is called <hi>Compunction,</hi> or the pricking of the heart, when ſinne becomes as a thorne in the ſpirit, and as a dagger at the heart; it is ſaid of Saint <hi>Peters</hi> hearers, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.37. <hi>That they were pricked at the heart;</hi> when the heart is ſmitten within, &amp; the thigh without, <hi>Ephraim's</hi> poſture, whom we find <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.19. thus bemoaning himſelfe under his chaſtiſement, <hi>Surely</hi> ſaith he, <hi>after that I was turned I repented, and after that I was inſtructed I ſmote upon my thigh; I was aſhamed, yea even con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded becauſe I did beare the reproach of my youth.</hi> When the inward greife of the heart doth expreſſe it ſelfe outwardly in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:111960:7"/>ſighes and teares, the affliction of the <hi>ſoule</hi> in that of the <hi>body</hi> by thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Iſ. Peluſiot</hi> termes them, Faſting and Sackcloth. <hi>I clothed me with ſackcloth and humbled my ſoule with faſting: Pſal.</hi> 35.13. When the ſoule and the body, which like <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> were confederates in ſinne, ſhall ſympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thize in their ſufferings, and exerciſe a mutuall revenge upon themſelves for the offences they have done; when with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> we ſhall waſh that bed with our teares, which we have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed with our ſinnes; when thoſe eies which before darted out rayes and ſparkles of Luſt, ſhall ſtreame forth waters to waſh, and thoſe haires curl'd and frizl'd up to provoke dalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, ſhall hang downe to wipe our Saviours feet, as <hi>Mary Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalens:</hi> In breife, when the ſoule comes to be ſurprized with the horror of it's owne guilt, and the feare of Gods Judgments, and is more afflicted with bitterneſſe at the review of the dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt and moſt adored ſinne, then ever it was affected with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the commiſſion of it.</p>
            <p>The 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> thing implied in this active humiliation, is a taking of ſhame to our ſelves, and giving God the glory of his Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, according to the Counſell of <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> to <hi>Achan, My ſonne give God the glory.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 7 19.</note> This is called the confeſſion of our ſinne and acceptance of our puniſhment, as in that ſignall place, <hi>Lev.</hi> 26.41. (a place very worthy our notice, as in which we may read, both our duty and hopes in this our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent diſtreſſe,) The Lord having there muſtered before the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> a whole Army of plagues, which he threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens to let in upon them in caſe of diſobedience, and from time to time to recruit againſt them with the vaſt acceſſion of new and ſeven times greater calamities in caſe of Rebellion, opens a doore of hope unto them, even in the very worſt condition, <hi>If they ſhall confeſſe their iniquity, and the iniquity of their Fathers, and their treſpaſſes which they have treſpaſſed againſt me, and that they have walked contrary to me, and that I alſo have walked contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to them, and have brought them into the Land of their enemies;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:111960:7"/>if then their uncircumciſed heart be humbled, and they then accept of the puniſhment of their iniquity, Then I will remember my Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and I will remember their Land.</hi> An humbled ſpirit is moſt ſevere to it ſelfe, tranſlates not the fault upon others, much leſſe chargeth God with ſeverity.<note place="margin">Job. 7.20.</note> 
               <hi>I have ſinned, and what ſhall I doe unto thee oh thou preſerver of men?</hi> ſaith <hi>Job</hi> upon the dunghill. <hi>He putteth his mouth in the duſt, ſaith</hi> Ieremie, <hi>if ſo be there may be hope. It is the Lords mercy that we are not conſumed,</hi> Lam 3.22. <hi>&amp;</hi> 29. <hi>I was dumbe and opened not my mouth, becauſe thou Lord didſt it, ſaith</hi> David, Pſal. 39.9. <hi>Rehoboam</hi> his Princes and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple humbling themſelves, though God threaten to leave them in the hand of the <hi>Egyptians</hi> (now come up with a great Army againſt them) yet acknowledge <hi>The Lord is righteous,</hi> 2 Chron. 12. <hi>O. O Lord to us belongs confuſion of face, to our Kings, to our Princes, and to our Fathers, becauſe we have ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee,</hi> [was the confeſſion of <hi>Daniel</hi> ſetting his face to ſeeke God by prayer and ſupplication with faſting, and ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloath, and aſhes,] <hi>but to our God belong mercies, and forgiveneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, though we have rebelled againſt him,</hi> Dan. 9.8.9. <hi>I will beare the indignation of the Lord,</hi> (ſaith the Church in <hi>Micah,</hi>) <hi>becauſe I have ſinned againſt him,</hi> Mic. 7.9. It is the courſe of ſome of our Courts of juſtice, that the delinquent after ſentence can obtaine no mitigation of his puniſhment, nor diſcharge from his impriſonment, till he acknowledge his offence and the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of their proceedings againſt him; this may ſeeme hard, 'tis poſſible in the Courts of men the innocent may ſuffer, no injuſtice poſſible from the Court of heaven, It is the rule of that Court, no relaxation, or mercy to be expected thence till we confeſſe the demerits of our ſinnes, and the righteouſneſſe of Gods Iudgements; and therefore the Prophet <hi>David</hi> held this courſe in the confeſſion of his ſinnes and ſupplication for pardon: <hi>I acknowledge my tranſgreſsions, and my ſinne is ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me: againſt thee only have I ſinned and done evill in thy ſight, that thou mighteſt be juſtified when thou ſpeakeſt, and cleare when
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:111960:8"/>thou judgeſt. Pſal.</hi> 51.3, 4. The Lamenting Prophet in that Sea of wrath let in upon Iudah, gives God the glory of his juſtice. <hi>Lam.</hi> 1.18. <hi>The Lord is righteous, for I have rebelled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his commandement.</hi> And this he doth by way of Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation too. <hi>Heare I pray you all people and behold my ſorrow, my Virgins and my Young men are gone into captivity. It is the Lord</hi> ſaith Eli, <hi>let him do what ſeemeth him good.</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.18. This acceptance of their puniſhment was imported in the poſture of the penitents <hi>ſtanding before the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 20.13. N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem. 9.2.</note> It is ſtoried of <hi>Mauri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> the Emperour, that when his children were murdered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his eyes (as once were <hi>Zedekiahs</hi> before his) and himſelfe after received the ſentence of death, he cryed out <hi>Iuſtus es Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, &amp; rectum judicium tuum. Righteous art thou, O Lord, and juſt are thy judgements.</hi> Theſe the ſpeeches, this the deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of an humbled ſpirit: And thus much in anſwere to the firſt Queſtion, what it is to be <hi>humbled,</hi> the neglect whereof ſtands here charged againſt the Iewes. <hi>They were not humbled unto this day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I proceed to the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. Why, when Gods judgements are up. on a people, then 'tis high time for them to <hi>humble themſelves?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the ſatisfaction whereof, I muſt deſire you to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice that after ſins committed there are 3 ſeaſons for a man or Nation <hi>to humble themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt immediately upon their Commiſſion, this indeed is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the beſt opportunity, repentance in the Fathers language is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the great medicine to ſalvation,</hi> and we know that a Soveraigne remedie will ſpeed the cure, if applied while the ſore is freſh. 'Tis in the wounds of the ſoule as thoſe of the body, thoſe that are long delayed are healed with more paine and difficulty. That humiliation never miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carries of the <hi>bleſsing,</hi> which (as <hi>Jacob</hi> did <hi>Eſau</hi>) <hi>ſhall take ſinne by the heele;</hi> when they ſhall come as twinnes into the world, ſinne the firſt borne ſhall be deſtroyed like thoſe of the <hi>Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and the elder not only ſerve the younger but as <hi>Joſephs</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:111960:8"/>brethren, or like <hi>Dagon</hi> before the Arke, ſhall fall downe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him. <hi>Alexander</hi> being askt how he made himſelfe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of <hi>Greece</hi> returned anſwere <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>by making no delay;</hi> ſhould we put the ſame queſtion to <hi>David,</hi> and demand how he obteined pardon for his ſinne in numbring the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, he would make us the like anſwere, by not deferring to humble himſelfe, no ſooner was the fact done <hi>but his heart ſmote him.</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.10. This was Saint <hi>Peters</hi> ſeaſon after the abnegation of his Maſter and perjury. <hi>The Cocke crew, Ieſus look't backe,</hi> and <hi>Peter immediately went forth and wept bitterly</hi> Matt. 26.75. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the ſame night was conſcious both to his ſinne and repentance, his wound and his cure.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chryſhom.</hi> 53.</note> This indeed is the handle of opportunity, the <hi>locke of time</hi> to humble our ſelves; and bleſſed are they that lay hold upon it.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ſeaſon of humiliation is then when the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience convinced of ſinne committed, beginnes to be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted with the apprehenſions of wrath, when the ſoule comes to ſee its guilt and is affraid of Gods judgements, and therefore makes haſt to agree with God offended while he is in the <hi>way,</hi> and to ſtop the <hi>Decree of wrath</hi> before it come forth, this opportunity deſerves it's praiſe, but (as 'tis ſaid of ſome of <hi>Davids</hi> worthies) <hi>in the ſecond place.</hi> That perſon un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Iudiciall Law, that being guilty of man ſlaughter reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the <hi>City of refuge,</hi> before he was overtaken by the aven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of bloud, ſaved his life, ſo ſhall that man that nation theirs, who underſtanding themſelves in danger of Gods wrath by reaſon of ſinne ſhall fly to the throne of grace and by unfained contrition lay hold upon the hornes of the Altar, before the meſſengers of wrath have layd hold upon them. <hi>But unto the King of Iudah which ſent you to enquire of the Lord, thus ſhall ye ſay unto him, becauſe thine heart was tender and thou haſt humbled thy ſelfe before the Lord, when thou heard'ſt that I ſpake againſt this place and againſt the Inhabitants thereof, that they
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:111960:9"/>ſhould become a deſolation and a curſe, and haſt rent thy cloathes and wept before me, I have alſo heard thee, ſaith the Lord. Behold there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I will gather thee unto thy fathers, &amp; thou ſhalt be gathered un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy grave in peace, and thine eyes ſhall not ſee all the evill which I will bring upon this place,</hi> it was ſpoken of good King <hi>Ioſiah.</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 22.19.</p>
            <p>The third and laſt opportunity for a people to humble themſelves, is when the <hi>Decree</hi> is broken forth, and the wrath of God is actually upon them, when the ſmart of the rodd makes them ſenſible of their ſinne, as it is ſayd of Iſrael <hi>Pſ.</hi> 78.34. <hi>When he ſlew them, then they ſought him, and enquired earely after God.</hi> This was <hi>Mannaſſeh</hi> his ſeaſon, as vile a wretch as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver breathed upon the earth, a very prodigie of wickedneſſe yet when he was in affliction, when his chaines were upon him <hi>then</hi> he <hi>ſought the Lord and humbled himſelfe greatly.</hi> 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 33.11. <hi>A prudent man foreſeeth the evill and hideth himſelfe. Prov.</hi> 22.3. Sees the Calamity in it's commination and prevents it in the threatning; ſees it firſt, and, as it is ſayd of the <hi>man</hi> and the <hi>Baſiliske,</hi> kils it by having the firſt ſight of it; while the cloud of wrath is but like that of <hi>Eliah,</hi> a hands-breadth, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees a tempeſt, and makes haſt for ſhelter. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a foole will be inſtructed while the rod is upon his backe; chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren when they ſmart will cry and begge, and promiſe never to do ſo againe. The racke of a great Plague will extort a confeſſion from obſtinate Pharaoh. <hi>I have ſinned this time, the Lord is Righteous and I and my people are wicked. Exod.</hi> 9.27. When the judgement is not onely at the doore, but entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the houſe,<note place="margin">Quis rogo interfici al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terum jux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ſe videt &amp; ipſe non metu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it? &amp;c. <hi>Salv.</hi>
               </note> and ſhall take away one here, another there, and all are in danger, will not every one be affraid? If the Lion roare, will not the beaſt tremble, much more when he ſhall come and ſeize upon his prey? Is it not time for the whole Towne to come in when their houſes are on fire, with water to quench it? It was high time for <hi>Aaron</hi> to ſtand in the gapp when the Plague had made a breach upon the People.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:111960:9"/>
               <hi>And</hi> Moſes <hi>ſaid unto</hi> Aaron, <hi>Take a Cenſer and put fire therein from off the Altar, and goe quickely unto the congregation, and make an autonement for them, for there is wrath gone out from the Lord, the plague is begun.</hi> Numb. 16.46. Such caſes as this admit no delayes, as <hi>Meſſadamus</hi> was wont to ſay of himſelfe, <hi>Know no to morrow:</hi> a little neglect here may undoe a Kingdome, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſerious things to morrow,</hi> coſt him deere that ſpake it, both his <hi>life</hi> and <hi>Thebes.</hi> In ſuch times as theſe, who knowes what a day, ſome few houres may bring forth? <hi>Sodom</hi> and thoſe ſiſter Cities had a faire morne, the Sun roſe glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, but never had people in the world a more terrible day. High time therefore it is when Gods hand is exalted in the way of his Judgements, for a people, a Nation, <hi>to humble themſelves,</hi> The neceſſity thereof will evidently appeare from the conſideration of theſe particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the ſound of this <hi>Trumpet</hi> is the laſt <hi>ſummons</hi> God gives a Rebellious people, it is the laſt <hi>Flagg</hi> that he hangs out, if they ſubmit not and yeild then, nothing to be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted at Gods hand but utter ruine. It is ſtoried of the victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Tamerlaine</hi> that great ſcourge of the <hi>Ottoman Empire,</hi> that when he advanc't againſt any Towne or City, ſo ſoone as he was ſet downe before it; the firſt day his Tents were all ſpread with <hi>white,</hi> a colour of Clemency, importing to them that if they would preſently ſurrender they ſhould be receiv'd into Mercy; if notwithſtanding this tender, they ſhould yet ſtand out againſt him the next day his <hi>Pavilion</hi> was cloth'd with <hi>red,</hi> a colour of bloud, to give them to underſtand his ſeveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; If neither of theſe two prevailed for a ſurrender, the third day the ſame Tents were all hung with <hi>blacke,</hi> to let them know that now all overtures of mercy were paſt, and that now they muſt expect whatſoever calamity the fury of a conquering e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy could bring upon them. Such a courſe it is that God holds with a ſinfull people, according to the rule he himſelfe gave unto the Jewes in their warres <hi>Deut.</hi> 20.10. <hi>He firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimes
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:111960:10"/>peace,</hi> holds out the white Flagg, ſummons them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance by the tenders of mercy; <hi>Go,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim theſe words towards the North and ſay; Returne, O backſliding</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and I will not cauſe mine anger to fall upon you; for I am mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull</hi> (ſaith the Lord,) <hi>and I will not cauſe mine anger to fall upon you. Ier.</hi> 3.12. If this gentler invitation prevaile not upon their love, he next ſends forth his <hi>Rod-Herald</hi> to make ſuch a ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons as may worke upon their feare; <hi>Heare ye the Rod and who hath appointed it;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Micah. 6.9.</note> This is <hi>Gods Red Flagg,</hi> and the laſt he holds out to ſinners with conditions of peaces: If the <hi>Rod</hi> cannot teach a People their duty, nor the ſeverity of Iudgements up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Land inſtruct the Inhabitants in Righteouſneſſe, if a Nation remaine deafe at the thunder of Gods loud voice, this obſtinacy obſtructes all the doores of hope, all the paſſages of mercy, God hangs out againſt them the <hi>blacke Enſigne</hi> of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Obſtinacy under Judgements raiſeth a ſin to the very <hi>height,</hi> it fills up the <hi>bag,</hi> &amp; compleats the meaſure of a peoples iniquity, and leaves ſin uncapable of greater aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. In the fourth of <hi>Amos</hi> God ſets forth the ſinne of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> arrived as it were at the <hi>non ultra</hi> of ſinfullneſſe, further then which it could hardly goe; that notwithſtanding the variety and extremity of the greateſt Iudgements upon them they relented not, nor returned unto God; it is the burden of every charge by a <hi>patheticall ſcheme</hi> which the <hi>Rhetoricians</hi> call <hi>Epiſtrophe</hi> or <hi>converſion,</hi> there five times repeated, <hi>Yet have they not returned unto me, ſaith the Lord: I have ſent among you peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence after the manner of</hi> Egypt, <hi>your young men have I ſlaine with the ſword, and have taken away your horſes, and I have made the ſtinke of your Camps to come up into your noſtrils, yet have ye not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned unto me, ſaith the Lord. I have overthrowne ſome of you, as God overthrew</hi> Sodom <hi>and</hi> Gomorrah, <hi>and ye were as a firebrand pluck't out out of the burning, yet have ye not returned unto me, ſaith the Lord.</hi> Oh this <hi>Yet</hi> hath an <hi>Emphaſis,</hi> an <hi>Accent</hi> upon it, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:111960:10"/>makes ſinne carry an infinite weight in the ballance of the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary: <hi>They are not humbled even unto this day,</hi> after all the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periences of divine Fury, heightned the Iewes ſinnes beyond an expreſſion. To relapſe into the ſame offence after puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment doubles the malefactors guilt, and deprives him of the Favour of the Iudge; but to ſinne upon the racke, under the plague, while <hi>Gods markes</hi> are upon them, renders ſinne almoſt incapable of forgiveneſſe. <hi>O Lord are not thine eyes upon the truth? thou haſt ſtricken them but they have not grieved, thou haſt conſumed them but they have refuſed to receive correction, they have made their faces harder then a rocke, they have refuſed to returne, Jer.</hi> 5.3. It followeth at the ſeaventh verſe. <hi>How ſhall I pardon thee for this?</hi> Oh there is a tranſcendent malignity in that ſin which God that is infinite in mercy, as it were knowes not how to pardon! The Pſalmiſt mentions it as the greateſt ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravation of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> Rebellion againſt God, <hi>that they ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned yet more, by provoking the moſt High in the wilderneſſe,</hi> a place wherein God had given them ſo many ocular demonſtrations of his indignation againſt their Rebellion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.17. yea 'tis added (if it be capable of any further degree of guilt) <hi>The wrath of the Lord came upon them and ſlew the fatteſt of them, and ſmote downe the choſen men of</hi> Iſrael: <hi>yet for all this they ſinned ſtill,</hi> verſ. 31, 32. There is onely one place more I ſhall minde you of, I beſeech you to lay it to heart, I almoſt tremble to recite it, becauſe I greatly feare, and I am perſwaded, your owne hearts will beare me witneſſe this day, that the guilt of that ſinne lyes heavy upon the moſt of us: the place is <hi>Iſa.</hi> 22.12. and ſome verſes following. <hi>In that day</hi> (viz. <hi>a day of trouble and treading downe, and perplexity by the Lord of Hoſts,</hi> as 'tis called verſ. 5.) <hi>did the Lord of Hoſts call to weeping, and to mourning, and to baldneſſe, and to girding with ſackcloath, and behold joy and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſlaying Oxen and killing Sheepe, eating fleſh an drinking wine; eating and drinking for tomorrow we ſhall dye, And it was revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in mine eares by the Lord of Hoſts; Surely this iniquity ſhall not
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:111960:11"/>be purged from you till ye dye, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">ly. Not to be humbled in times of diſtreſſe is the <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter</hi> of a hopeleſſe People, the <hi>blacke marke</hi> upon a man or Nation deſigned to ruine. It is the property of the damned in Hell, to be tormented and ſinne, to be tormented and to blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme God, becauſe of their torments. To be more obſtinate under plagues and to drive on then in ſinne, when God takes off their Chariot wheels, and declares himſelf manifeſtly from heaven againſt them, is the ſigne of a <hi>Pharaoh's</hi> heart, and of that people that God will drowne in the <hi>red Sea</hi> of his wrath. <hi>For the people turneth not unto him that ſmiteth them, neither doe they ſeeke the Lord of Hoſts, Therefore the Lord will cut off from</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael <hi>head and taile branch and ruſh in one day,</hi> Iſa. 9.13, 14. <hi>This is a Nation that obeyeth not the voice of the Lord their God, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth correction, Truth is periſhed and is cut off from their mouth. Cut off thine haire, ôh</hi> Ieruſalem, <hi>and caſt it away, and take up a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation upon high places, for the Lord hath rejected and forſaken the generation of his wrath. Jer.</hi> 7.28, 29. A Father that after all gentle wayes frequently tried without ſucceſſe, at laſt finds his child obſtinate under the rod, gives him over as a loſt child. A Chirurgion that after all corroſions and lancings and mutilation of joints, finds the Gangrene to ſpread further into the body, lookes upon his patient, as hopeleſſe of Cure. And King <hi>Ahaztreſpaſſed yet more in his deſtreſſe;</hi> and the Holy Ghoſt points him out to the world as an eternall object of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach and wonder<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>This is that King</hi> Ahaz! as if he had ſaid, Oh all ye that paſſe by, did ye ever heare of ſuch a man as this? did ye ever read of one whom the ſenſe of judgements embit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd into the height of impiety? why this is the man. <hi>This is that King</hi> Ahaz. Theſe ſeverer remedies are the laſt courſe God takes, if that faile, <hi>Conclamatum eſt,</hi> the caſe is deſperate, you may write upon their Gates, THE LORD HAVE MERCY UPON THEM. <hi>The Lord ſhall ſmite</hi> Egypt, (ſaith the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi>) <hi>he ſhall ſmite and heale is, and the ſhall
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:111960:11"/>returne even to the Lord, and he ſhall be intreated of them, and he ſhall heale them.</hi> Iſa. 19.22. Gods Rod (as 'tis ſaid of <hi>Achilles</hi> ſpeare) hath a vertue to heale thoſe wounds it makes. Now how the Lord ſmote <hi>Egypt</hi> to heale it, we read at the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> verſe of that Chapter. <hi>I will ſet the Egyptians againſt the Egyptians, and they ſhall fight every one againſt his brother, and every one againſt his neighbour, City againſt City, and Kingdome againſt Kingdome.</hi> The Example applies it ſelfe. This one would thinke a ſtrange courſe, to make whole by daſhing in peices, to bring things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to order by confuſion, to reconcile by diſſention, to raiſe up the happineſſe of a people upon the foundation of a civill Warre. Yet this is the courſe ſometimes of the great Phiſitian of Nations, who can bring light out of darkeneſſe, and allay the moſt violent poyſon into an Antidote: <hi>he will ſmite and heale them.</hi> if this way ſucced not we may conclude then that <hi>their wound is greivous and their bruiſe incurable,</hi> Ier 30.12.</p>
            <p>The Scripture ſets forth this Method of Gods dealing with Nations under the type of ſundry moſt expreſſive Metaphors; <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.4.5. <hi>O</hi> Ephraim, <hi>what ſhall I doe unto thee? O</hi> Iudah <hi>what ſhall I doe unto thee? I have hewen them by my Prophets, and ſlaine them by the words of my mouth, and thy judgements are as the light that goeth forth.</hi> A Trope taken from the Maſon or Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penter who doth ſquare and cut the ſtone or timber to make it ſit for the building, or ſuch purpoſes as they are deſigned to by the Artificer, unto which if after all their paines they prove uſeleſſe and unſerviceable, then he throwes them away as good for nothing, <hi>&amp; I have ſlaine them by the words of my mouth.</hi> The Prophets I have ſent, have denounc't againſt them all the curſes in the booke of the Law, and declared to them that they are but dead men, if they perſervere in their ſinnes, yea more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, <hi>and thy Iudgements have beene like the light that goeth forth.</hi> Thou Lord haſt made knowne thy diſpleaſure againſt them in the ſight of the Nations; <hi>but they like men have tranſgreſſed, they have dealt treacherouſly againſt me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> God having ran his <hi>whole
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:111960:12"/>courſe</hi> with them, ſeemes not now as it were to know what fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to doe. <hi>O</hi> Ephraim <hi>what ſhall I doe unto thee? O</hi> Judah <hi>what ſhall I do unto thee?</hi> The Lord in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 24.3. ſets forth the deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate filthineſſe of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> by a <hi>pot</hi> whoſe ſcum could not be conſumed; the Prophet there is commanded to ſet on a pot<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Set it on and alſo poure water into it,</hi> &amp; then to put in the beſt pieces of fleſh, &amp; every choice bone, &amp; after that to make them boile; when this courſe prevailes not to get out the ſcumme, the Prophet from God pronounceth a <hi>Woe</hi> againſt it. <hi>Wherefore thus ſaith the Lord God, Woe to the bloudy City, to the pot whoſe ſcumme is therein, and whoſe ſcumme is not gone out of it.</hi> But yet God doth not give it off here, there's one courſe remaines yet to purge out the ſcumme, and that he takes, if any thing can doe it 'tis that: He commands the Prophet to empty the pot, to make the pile for fire great, to heape on wood and kindle the fire, and then to ſet the pot thus empty upon it, that the braſſe might be hot and burne, that the filthineſſe might be <hi>molten in it and the ſcumme conſumed;</hi> now becauſe after all this her <hi>filthineſſe</hi> remained, and her <hi>great ſcumme went not out of her:</hi> The Lord concludes her as an incurable City under that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall ſentence, at the 13 verſ. <hi>In thy filthineſſe is lewdneſſe; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I have purged thee and thou waſt not purged, thou ſhalt not be purged from thy filthineſſe any more, untill I have cauſed my fury to reſt upon thee;</hi> The Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> yet further illuſtrates the deſperate eſtate of that people whom the extremity of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe cannot reclaime from their wickedneſſe by a moſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite ſimilitude taken from the Refiners, who by melting their mettall in the fire make a ſeperation of the good mettall from the droſſe. <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.7. <hi>I will melt them and try them, for what ſhall I doe for the daughter of my people?</hi> as if he had ſaid, If there be any thing ſound or of worth in a droſſie cankred people, it cannot be preſerved, but onely by melting them in the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace, this currupted Nation cannot otherwiſe be <hi>ſaved but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the fire.</hi> Now with how great labour and exactneſſe God
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:111960:12"/>performes this triall, the Prophet expreſſeth <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.28, 29. where he brings in God complaining againſt <hi>Iudah. They are greivous revolters walking with ſlanders, they are braſſe and Iron, they are all corrupters, the bellowes are burnt, the lead is conſumed of the fire, the founder melteth in vaine, for the wicked are not pluck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away. Malitiae corum non ſunt conſumptae,</hi> their wickedneſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es are not conſumed and purged by the refining fire of Gods Judgments. Their iniquity is ſo incorporated that though the <hi>bellowes be burnt, (i.e.)</hi> the voyce of the <hi>rod</hi> as well as the <hi>Prophet</hi> made hoarſe and quite ſpent with crying unto them to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble themſelves, the lead uſed for the ſeparation of the droſſe from the better mettall was all waſted in the fire, yet they were not purified, their droſſe did ſtill cleave unto them; no extremity of calamity could part them and their ſinnes, and therefore it followes at the next verſe. <hi>Reprobate ſilver ſhall men call them, becauſe the Lord hath rejected them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, God doth eſpecially obſerve the ſeverall deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the inhabitants of a land when his judgments are up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them; his pure eye runns to and fro to ſee how men ſtand affected, and to take notice what men do, and ſay in the times of diſtreſſe. It was a fearefull viſitation which God threatens <hi>Iudah</hi> with. <hi>Ier.</hi> 8.3. where the prophet tells them, that ſo great ſhould their calamity be, that <hi>Death ſhould be choſen rather then life.</hi> at the 6 verſe he repreſents God as it were going fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> City to City, from houſe to houſe, and from company to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and <hi>there</hi> liſtening to heare what the people would doe and ſay in the day of their feares. <hi>I hearkened and heard, but they ſpake not aright, no man repented him of the evell, ſaying, what have I done?</hi> They ſpake happily much, (as God helpe us too many now) but they ſpake not as they ſhould; <hi>they ſpake not aright,</hi> for they repented not of their wickedneſſe, <hi>no man ſayd, what have I done?</hi> What a paucity is there in the world who in times of diſtreſſe ſpeake that which God expects and deſires to heare? amongſt all the talke of the times how rare is
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:111960:13"/>that of repentance, the erre of teares, and the voyce of weeping, thoſe ſighes and groanes which the penitent ſoule ſends up to heaven as Ambaſſadours to the throne of grace for mercy? How few ſuch ſpeakers as the Prophet <hi>Malachi</hi> mentions? <hi>Then they that feared the Lord ſpake often one to another, and the Lord hearkened and heard it, and a booke of Remembrance was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten before him for them that feared the Lord, and that thought upon his name. Mal.</hi> 3.16. Where ſhall God find a ſelfe-humbling, ſelfe-condemning ſinner, who ſenſible of his owne guilt, ſaith, <hi>What have I done?</hi> Beloved, that great God, before whom all things are naked, that knowes the ſecrets of all hearts, is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent amongſt us at this time in the midſt of the <hi>Temple,</hi> and ſees with what devotion or with what want of it we ſtand in his <hi>Courts,</hi> he takes notice how the pulſe of every one of our hearts beats, there's never a thought which he marks not, never a ſigh fetcht in private but he ſets down in his book, never a tear ſhed in our Cloſets that he ſaves not in his bottle; he obſerves too who ſtands off and comes not in this day to afflict his ſoule, as if he had no ſinnes to procure the Judgements that are now upon us, or no ſence to feele them. There's never a perſon carowſing at the Taverne, nor ſwearing in the ſtreets, no <hi>Zimri</hi> and <hi>Cosby</hi> acting their Luſts, none idle or happly worſe imployed in the houſe, when the Aſſemblies are mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the Church, that he obſerves not. Never a ſinne this day committed but he ſeales up in his bagge, the ſinnes that at other times might be mitigated by an excuſe, committed on this day grow into a preſumption beyond an Apology, God writes them in Capitall Letters with a pen of a Diamond; he doth at all times abhorre a proud and unhumbled ſoule, ſuch a one this day is an abomination, the ſoule that is not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted at ſuch times as this, ſhall be cut off <hi>from the people;</hi> a <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite and broken heart</hi> is the onely <hi>ſacrifice</hi> that can propitiate him in this <hi>day of attonement.</hi> If we conſult the ſacred Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, we ſhall not find a more perfect Regiſter of any thing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:111960:13"/>then of ſuch, both perſons, and People, as humbled themſelves under Gods mighty hand ſtretcht our in Judgement againſt them, and of ſuch as at theſe times remained obſtinate and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent; thoſe he remembers to their advantage, and menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with praiſe, theſe he records with indignation, and ſets a <hi>ſtigma</hi> a brand of infamy upon them, for their laſting reproach ſo long as thoſe ſacred monuments ſhall remain in the world; I can but point at one or two inſtances of many. In 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 32.25. we read of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> whom God had miraculouſly reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from a dangerous ſickneſſe, and granted 15 yeares more to his life, when his terme was expired, that <hi>he rendred not againe according to the benefit done unto him, for his heart was lifted up, therefore there was wrath upon him and upon Judah and Jeruſalem. Notwithſtanding Hezekiah humbled himſelfe for the pride of his heart (both he and the Inhabitants of Jeruſalem:) ſo that the wrath of the Lord came not upon them in the dayes of Hezekiah.</hi> In the next Chapter we have the ſtory of the unparallel'd wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe of <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> his Son, and how vanquiſh't, by the King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> he was carryed away captive in fetters to <hi>Babylon,</hi> and there when he was in affliction how he beſought the Lord his God, and <hi>humbled himſelfe greatly.</hi> On the other ſide it ſtands as a perpetuall blot upon the name of <hi>Amon</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> that though he had ſinned as his Father had done, <hi>yet he humbled not himſelfe, but Amon treſpaſſed more and more.</hi> And upon <hi>Zedekiah chap.</hi> 36.12. <hi>that he did that which was evill in the ſight of the Lord his God, and humbled not himſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Ieremiah the Prophet ſpeaking from the mouth of the Lord.</hi> Examples in this kind would ſwell beyond the time. I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten.</p>
            <p n="5">5ly There's nothing in the world can ſtand in the gapp to ſtop God marching againſt us in the way of his Judgements, and keepe out a Torrent of wrath flowing in upon a Kingdom, but only the humbling of our ſelves. Our eyes for the moſt part in times of diſtreſſe like <hi>Solomons fooles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 17.24.</note> are at the <hi>ends
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:111960:14"/>of the earth,</hi> we looke upon our forces abroad, and our fortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations at home, like thoſe in <hi>Iſai.</hi> 22.8. that in that day did looke unto the <hi>Armories,</hi> made up their breaches, drew in their waters, broke downe their houſes to fortifie the wall, inlarged their trenches and let in the poole; and theſe things are not to be neglected, but here was their fault, and I feare ours, <hi>they looked not to the maker thereof,</hi> they had no reſpect unto God, no care by the humiliation of themſelves in weeping and mourning, (a duty which the Lord of Hoſts call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for at their hands at that time, as the only meanes of their ſafety and preſervation) to make him propitious to them, to appeaſe his wrath, and engage him for them, who if <hi>he keepe not the City, the watchman watcheth but in vaine.</hi> it is our <hi>God</hi> that is the <hi>Pignus Imperii,</hi> the <hi>Palladium,</hi> and <hi>Ancile</hi> of our Cities. While we enjoy his protection and preſence, we may not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay of them as they did of <hi>Sparta,</hi> that their <hi>men</hi> were their walls, but our God, <hi>ſalvation will the Lord appoint for walls and bulwarkes.</hi> no weapon ſhall proſper againſt the City that is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by God; hee'le ſend Armies from heaven to fight for us, when we have none in the field. <hi>They fought from heaven, the ſtarres in their courſes fought againſt Siſera.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judg. 5.20.</note> 
               <hi>The river Kiſhon ſwept them away, even that ancient River, the River Kiſhon.</hi> Halfe a Regiment with <hi>Gideon,</hi> when God goes Generall with them into the field, ſhall be more then enough to diſcomfit the whole hoſt of <hi>Midian.</hi> he can ſtrike the beſiegers with a Panicke feare, and make them fly at the onely imagined noyſe of Horſes and Chariots. On the other ſide, if God be againſt us, it availes not what our proviſions, and fortifications be, or how many thouſand are for us. All the Caſtles, and Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warkes, and Armies in the world cannot protect us, from God as an enemy. <hi>Aiguanus</hi> tells us of a <hi>Prince,</hi> who being call'd in by the Inhabitants of a City to their aſſiſtance, and the rather to perſwade him, being aſſured that the place was verytenible, well provided, and fortified; The Prince return'd anſwere de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireing
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:111960:14"/>to know whether their city were covered above, ſo that Gods anger could not fall from heaven upon them; ſignifying unto them, that it was a vaine thing to hope to ſecure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the ſtrength of walls, and the helpe of men, while ſinne layed them open to the wrath of God. The ſinnes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are more to be feared, then the enemies without. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> was a voice heard from heaven by the Tyrant <hi>Phocas,</hi> who thought after all his villanie to preſerve himſelfe by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnableneſſe of the place; <hi>wickedneſſe is within,</hi> the City ſhall be deſtroyed. I read of a people that, when <hi>Alexander</hi> ſent unto them to know what it was they moſt feared; (he ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed they would have ſaid himſelfe.) but they anſwered, that they were moſt affraid <hi>leſt heaven ſhould fall upon them:</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed this is moſt to be feared, leſt the wrath of the God of heaven fall upon us; after all our fortifications we lye open to <hi>heaven,</hi> and there's no way to ſecure our ſelves from an enemy thence, but by humbling our ſelves. Humiliation hath often made up the breaches, when a whole nation hath beene ready to be overwhelm'd by an inundation of Judgements. As <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bigail</hi> once did <hi>David,</hi> it appeaſeth God in the height of his fury; it ſtands as the <hi>Raine. bow</hi> that God hath ſet in the Cloudes, which whenſoever he lookes upon he relents, and will not drowne that people in a deluge of wrath. <hi>Non poteſt orbis cadere, que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lacrymae ſuſtentant,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auſtin;</hi> the teares of contriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they are the Pillars of a Kingdome, the props that ſuſtaine and beare up the world that it doth not fall into it's primitive confuſion, Humiliation is that <hi>ſure Anchor of hope</hi> which hath ſaved the Church, and State from wracke, in the greateſt tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts upon both. God hath obtained his end when he ſees us proſtrate upon the ground, and yeelding our ſelves, his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation doth not fall ſo low, he cannot exerciſe vengeance upon them who revenge ſinne upon themſelves, nor deſtroy them that lie downe at his feete, and cry for mercy.<note place="margin">2 Chron. 12</note> 
               <hi>They have humbled themſelves,</hi> ſaith the Lord of <hi>Rehoboam, and his
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:111960:15"/>Princes, therefore I will grant them ſome deliverance, and my wrath ſhall not be powred upon them by the hand of Shiſhach.</hi> Goe, ſaith the Lord to thoſe Commiſſioners <hi>EZek.</hi> 9. <hi>Set a marke upon them,</hi> that they may be ſpared in the day of my wrath; They are <hi>mourners,</hi> they <hi>cry</hi> out for their owne and the ſinnes of the Nation. <hi>If my people that are called by my name ſhall humble themſelves, and pray, and ſeeke my face, and turne from their evill wayes; I will heare from heaven and have mercy, I will pardon their ſinne, and heale their Land.</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 7.14. We have an exellent example to this purpoſe in the 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Judges.</hi> The children of Iſrael fell from the ſervice of God to the ſervice of Idols, God ſells them that will not ſerve him to be ſlaves to their enemies, who vex and oppreſſe them full 18 yeares, (a long bondage,) this the condition of the people on the the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide of <hi>Iordan;</hi> and 'tis like to be as bad with thoſe on this ſide the river; The enemy is upon his march with a mighty Army: The People in diſtreſſe fly to God for aſſiſtance, and receive a cold anſwer from him, ſuch as might have diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged them from all hopes of deliverance; for firſt he upbraids them, with thoſe many deliverances he had wrought for them already. <hi>Did not I deliver you out of the hand of the Aegyptians, and the Amorites, and the Children of Amen, and the Zidonians? &amp;c.</hi> as if at this day he ſhould anſwere us of this place. Did I not deliver you from the Tyranny of the Pope, from the Spaniſh Armado; and the Gunpowder-treaſon? from the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny plots againſt the perſons of your Kings, and the peace of your State, from the fury of the peſtilence, and the terrour of death in ſundry battailes of late? <hi>Yet have ye forſaken me;</hi> and then concludes <hi>he will deliver them no more,</hi> but bids them go to the Gods they had choſen, and <hi>let them deliver them in the time of their trouble.</hi> In this caſe what ground had faith upon which to ſtirre up importunity to aske, or hope to expect ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and deliverance, when as God had flatly anſwered them that he would deliver the mno more? Why, yet this hope
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:111960:15"/>they have ſtill. <hi>The Lord is mercifull,</hi> he hath beene intreated to forgive when he hath purpoſed to puniſh, and to ſave when he had reſolved to deſtroy. It may be their ſighes and teares and prayers may overcome Gods reſolution, and move him to deliver them, though he hath ſaid he will deliver them no more. How e're they are reſolved to throw themſelves at his feete, if they muſt die they'le die there, if he will not helpe them in their diſtreſſe, they cannot finde any fault with him, they have deſerved no favour at his hands; if he will ſee them deſtroyed he may, but their hope is that notwithſtanding they have been a diſobedient people, yet the Lord will looke upon them now as an humbled people, and have compaſſion upon them. <hi>And they ſaid unto the Lord, we have ſinned, doe thou unto us as ſeemeth good unto thee; deliver us onely we pray thee this day.</hi> And to their humiliation they adde reformation, for it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes. <hi>They put away their ſtrange Gods from them,</hi> and now marke the ſucceſſe with God; why his heart is as it were melt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into pity towards them, for, ſaith the Text; <hi>His ſoule was greived for the miſery of Iſrael;</hi> and againſt his former declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on crownes their ſubmiſſion with a glorious victory.</p>
            <p>In the laſt place, it will appeare evidently as a truth written by a beame of the ſunne, that there is great cauſe why a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, when Gods hand is ſtretch't out in wrath againſt them, ſhould humble themſelves, if we doe but conſider how glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and dreadfull that God is whoſe hand is exalted in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and how vile creatures we are; and what a terrible thing his wrath is, and how impotent we are to ſtand againſt it. His Majeſty is ſo excellent, that the moſt glorious Seraphinis dare not behold it, but thorow the vayle of their wings, and then too dazelled with admiration, cry <hi>Holy, Holy, Holy, Lord God of Hoſts, the whole earth is full of his glory. Iſa.</hi> 6.3. Never yet had mortall man, even the moſt innocent, any glympſe of that glory, but did preſently humble and abhorre himſelfe. <hi>Woe is me</hi> (ſaith the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> at the 5. verſ. of the Chap.) <hi>for I
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:111960:16"/>am undone, becauſe I am a man of uncleane lipps, and I dwell in the midſt of a People of uncleane lipps, for mine eyes have ſeene the King, the Lord of Hoſts.</hi> Much more cauſe then have a ſinfull people to be abaſed, to be aſtoniſh't, and to tremble, to meet him in the way of his judgements, the infinite depth of whoſe wrath no created underſtanding is able to fathom. <hi>The wrath of a King, ſaith Solomon, is as the roareing of a Lion,</hi> when the Lion roares <hi>who will not tremble?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 19.12.</note> Yea but this is the wrath of a <hi>God,</hi> this ſpeakes an immenſity, an infiniteneſſe, we cannot conceive.<note place="margin">Judg. 8.21.</note> 
               <hi>As the mans is, ſo is his ſtrength;</hi> as <hi>God</hi> is ſo is his <hi>wrath;</hi> it is a <hi>wrath</hi> that doth virtually, and eminently containe all the terrors of the Creature. We read of ſtrange exquiſite tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments the Cruelty of Tyrants have invented, theſe all are but ſhadowes to the effects of his wrath. The ſcripture gives us ſome adumbrations of it by ſuch reſemblances, as ſpeake it to be a moſt terrible wrath. It is compared to fire the moſt active and terrible creature; the Philoſopher tells us that nothing can live in that Element; and our <hi>fire,</hi> in reſpect of that, is but like the fire that is painted upon the wall, and yet the poore creature muſt live for ever in it, God upholding it that it may feele the <hi>power of his wrath,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſay. 30.33.</note> to a <hi>River of fire and brimſtone;</hi> that carries ſomething more with it: The deluge of water was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dreadfull, it drowned a whole world, but ſuch a flood of fire and brimſtone, how horrible would that be? and what are the proudeſt ſinners to ſtand before it, who are but as ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? why, it carries away gates, and walls, and Caſtles, and Kingdomes, and Heaven, and Earth, and all with it. <hi>The earth ſhooke and trembled, the foundations of heaven moved, becauſe he was wroth,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.8. and ſhall poore man that is cruſhed before the moth be able to oppoſe himſelfe againſt it? <hi>Can thine heart endure, or thine hands he ſtrong in the day, that I ſhall deale with thee? EZek.</hi> 22.14. Haſt thou a hand to reſiſt it, or an heart to beare it? one drop of that wrath falling upon them, will turne the <hi>ſunne into darkeneſſe,</hi> and the <hi>moone</hi> into <hi>blood,</hi> and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:111960:16"/>make the <hi>ſtarres</hi> drop downe from heaven; one ſparkle thereof ſhall ſet on fire the Heavens, and the earth,<note place="margin">Matt. 24.29.</note> the whole frame of nature, and burne downe to the <hi>bottom of Hell. Lord, who knowes the power of thy wrath? For according to thy feare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 32 22.</note> 
               <hi>ſo is thy wrath.</hi> ſaith Moſes <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.11. Melancholy apprehenſions will fancy ſtrange feares, but imagination it ſelfe falls infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhort of the power of Gods wrath. ſhold God take and ſet a man upon hells brinke, that he might ſe the torments, and heare the cries of the damned there, his underſtanding cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely would be much inlarged to conceive, but yet never able to know what is the <hi>power of Gods wrath.</hi> O conſider this and tremble, ye that do not onely <hi>ſinne</hi> downe, but <hi>pray</hi> downe this wrath upon your ſelves, by thoſe fearefull imprecations <hi>God damne me,</hi> and <hi>The Divell take me.</hi> Little do theſe poore ſoules thinke what it is to be <hi>damned.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſay. 33.14.</note> Who can dwell with <hi>devoureing fire?</hi> who can dwell with <hi>everlaſting burnings?</hi> And yet this they muſt, upon whom God ſhewes forth the power of his wrath in their damnation: What ever vaine people now conceite of it, the time ſhall come when Kings, and great men, and rich men, cheife Captaines, and mighty men,<note place="margin">Rev. 6.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.16.</note> ſhall petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the mountaines and the rocks, to hide them from this <hi>wrath, Thou O Lord, even thou art to be feared,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.7.</note> 
               <hi>and who may ſtand in thy ſight when thou art angry?</hi> Now ſince Gods wrath is ſo terrible, when it beginnes to grow hot againſt a people, there is more then cauſe, it's high time for them to humble themſelves. I have done with the 2 firſt Queres, I deſcend now to the laſt, which brings the point nearer home, to ſhew what cauſe we of this Kingdome, and particularly wee of this place have to humble our ſelves; I cannot point at all particulars, I ſhall one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly touch theſe three.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, the great diſtreſſe, that is this day upon the whole kingdome; this is a <hi>Lamentation,</hi> and ſhould be for a <hi>Lamentation.</hi> we read in the 21. of <hi>Iudges,</hi> that when by the ſword of Civill warre, the Tribe of <hi>Benjamin</hi> was cut off and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:111960:17"/>deſtroyed, that the other Tribes came to the Houſe of God, and abode there untill even before the Lord, <hi>and lift up their voices, and wept ſore, ſaying. O Lord God of Iſrael, why is this come to paſſe in Iſrael, that there ſhould be this day one Tribe lacking in Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael? and the children of Iſrael,</hi> (ſaith the Text,) <hi>repented them for Benjamin their brother, and ſaid, There is one tribe cut off from Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael this day?</hi> We are met (Beloved) at this time in Gods houſe to humble ourſelves, and what cauſe of mourning have we for this Nation, wherein I will not ſay <hi>one Tribe is cut off already,</hi> but many of the heades and choſen men of every Tribe: and the whole remnant of this once populous flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Kingdome is ready to be deſtroyed by the bloody ſword of an inteſtine diſſention,<note place="margin">2 Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on. 20.23.</note> while we like thoſe earth-borne <hi>Thebans,</hi> or <hi>curſed Cananites,</hi> help to kill and deſtroy each other? When <hi>Ziglag</hi> was burnt with fire, at the very ſight of it <hi>David</hi> and his men wept ſo much that they could weepe no more. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 30.3. what greater reaſon have we to weepe at the ſight of the generall conflagration of our owne Country? Were there nothing to be lamented by us in this day of our Faſt, but the publique miſeries of this poore <hi>Kingdome,</hi> with how loud and fearefull a cry doe they call every one of us to mourning. <hi>Ye daughters of England weepe over me who cloathed you with ſcarlet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 1.24.</note> 
               <hi>and ſed you with the flower of wheate:</hi> How are the mighty fallen in the midſt of the Battaile? how are not only the weapons of warre, but all the abundance and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightes and glory of your peace periſhed? What cauſe have we (I ſay) not only with good <hi>Nehemiah</hi> to have our counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances ſad,<note place="margin">Nehem. 1.4.</note> and to ſit downe and weepe, and mourne, and faſt and pray before the God of heaven, but to wiſh with <hi>Jeremie, O that our heads were waters,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 9.4.</note> 
               <hi>and our eyes a fountaine of teares, that we might weepe day and night for the ſlaine of the daughter of our people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſecond cauſe we have to humble our ſelves at this time is the conſideration of every one of our owne ſinnes, and the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:111960:17"/>ſinne of the Nation, the guilt and provocation whereof have drawne downe upon our heads the great wrath, and indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our God. Teares were made only for ſin, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. God (ſaith Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>) hath implanted in us the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſorrow for no other thing in the world but ſinne;<note place="margin">Hon. <hi>7.</hi> ad pop. Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chenu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> in our Calamities we ſhould looke with the eye of contrition more upon our ſinnes then our ſufferings, and be more afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that we ſhould deſerve afflictions, then that we ſhould endure them. A <hi>Pharaoh</hi> will cry out of the Plague, and pray for the taking away of the death, repenting <hi>Iſrael</hi> prayes for the removall of their ſinne. <hi>Take away all our iniquity. Hoſ.</hi> 14.2. and indeed all other Calamities to this are in the ſame Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers words, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, bare names of Calamity, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp;c. ſin is only truly ſo.<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> Whatſoever bitterneſſe is in any affliction, is put into it by the malignity of ſin; and therefore the Godly who are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, men of teares, in their weeping have alwayes moſt lamented their ſinnes. When Gods wrath was incenſed againſt Iſrael to have deſtroyed them for the golden Calfe. Oh, ſaith <hi>Moſes, this people have ſinned a great ſinne, and yet now if thou wilt forgive their ſinne &amp;c. Exod</hi> 32 31. <hi>O my God,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ezra</hi> in the great diſtreſſe of his people, <hi>I am aſhamed and bluſh to lift up my face to thee, O my God, for our iniquities are increaſed over our heads, and our treſpaſſe is growne up unto the heavens Ezra</hi> 9.6. the ſame courſe is held by <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> and <hi>Daniel</hi> in their ſupplication, King <hi>David</hi> when the deſtroying Angel is ſheathing his ſword into <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> cries out, <hi>I have ſinned and I have done wickedly</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.17. <hi>Mine heart,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ieremy, within me is broken becauſe of the Prophets, my bones ſhake, I am like a drunken man, like a man whom wine hath overcome, becauſe of the Lord, and becauſe of the wordes of his holineſſe; for the Land is full of Adulterers, for becauſe of ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Land mournes, the pleaſant places of the wilderneſſe are dryed up; and their courſe is evill, and their force is not right. Ier.</hi> 23.9.10. O for ſome Jeremies to lament this over againe for this nation.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:111960:18"/>Teares that are ſhed for ſinne are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, commendable teares,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Orat.</hi> 21.</note> as <hi>Nazianzen</hi> tearmes them. The Philoſopher tells us that the dew of heaven and the raine from above, is farre more fertile then the waters from the fountaines and rivers below, and ſo are thoſe teares for ſinne then thoſe that are for afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And if ever people had cauſe to be humbled, to have their hearts broken, and their eyes run downe with rivers of waters for their owne ſinnes and the ſinnes of their Nation, then have we certainly this day. That we ſhould ſin away our peace, and thoſe bleſſings which made us glorious in the ſight of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; that we ſhould <hi>ſin</hi> our ſelves into all theſe miſeries that are now upon us; The greatneſſe of our preſent diſtreſſe teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies to our faces the greatneſſe of our ſinnes. God that never <hi>afflicts willingly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 3.33.</note> and when he doth, puniſhes <hi>citra condignum,</hi> leſſe then the <hi>deſert of our ſinnes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job. 11.6.</note> hath declared unto us the enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of our ſinne by the extremity of our puniſhment. <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem hath greivouſly ſinned,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 1.8.</note> ſaith the Prophet; <hi>And therefore is ſhe removed.</hi> We may ſay too this day, <hi>England</hi> hath greivouſly ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, therefore is ſhe greivouſly afflicted, <hi>her glory is removed and departed from her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet this is not all; the ſinnes whereby we firſt drew downe this great wrath upon our ſelves are not all the cauſe we have to be humbled at this time; no, there is ſomething more for which (were it but throughly reſented) all our <hi>hearts</hi> ſhould melt, all our <hi>bowells</hi> tremble, and all our <hi>Livers be poured</hi> out on the earth, like water before the Lord this day; and that is that we ſtill ſinne <hi>under Judgements,</hi> that we have not humbled our ſelves as yet under <hi>Gods mighty hand,</hi> that we have contracted the guilt of many <hi>new greivous ſinnes,</hi> even ſince the time that Gods hand hath beene upon us in ſo terrible a Judgement. Great cauſe hath every one of us to ſit downe and take up a Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation over his owne hard heart: <hi>Alas! What ſtone is my heart made of?</hi> The hardeſt <hi>marble will weepe,</hi> when the heaven is blacke with tempeſts above: though great clouds of Gods an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:111960:18"/>have hung a long time over our heads, and many ſtormes of wrath fallen upon us, yet my <hi>heart</hi> mournes not. The <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damant,</hi> that they ſay, will onely expell vaine feares; no reall feares no terrour of preſent Judgements can make any impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of feare upon my heart. The Naturaliſt tells us too that the <hi>Adamant</hi> is broken with Goats bloud, but neither the bloud of Jeſus Chriſt that <hi>ſcape-Goate,</hi> nor that of ſo many thouſands of our brethren that have beene ſlaine, have melted my heart into teares of Contrition. What? is it a <hi>rocke?</hi> why the rocke when ſtrooke but twice by the <hi>rod</hi> of <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſent forth waters <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly,</hi> ſaith the Text, <hi>Num.</hi> 20.11. But God hath often ſmitten us with <hi>his rod,</hi> and yet no waters of repentance flow from my hard impenitent heart. Oh this ſets our condition in the very depth of miſery, and almoſt beyond the hopes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, that we ſinne ſtill, that we repent not <hi>under Judgements.</hi> What flouds of teares are ſufficient to deplore this impeniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; <hi>O our God,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ezra, what ſhall we ſay after all this? for we have forſaken thy Commandements,</hi> Ezr. 9.10. This is that which <hi>Daniel</hi> inſiſteth upon as the maine aggravation of the ſinne of <hi>Judah, Dan.</hi> 9.12. that though the like had not beene done <hi>under heaven,</hi> as had beene done upon <hi>Jeruſalem, Though,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>all this be come upon us, yet made we not our prayer before the Lord our God, that we might turne from our iniquities, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand thy truth.</hi> Oh Beloved, let this conſideration be like <hi>Moſes rod</hi> to ſtrike water out of our ſtony hearts, that the <hi>plague</hi> of ſinne is upon us, while we ſigh and groane and dye under the plague of Judgements; Let us lament that we have not la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented for our ſinnes, and ſay, <hi>The Lord pardon our Impeniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, the Lord forgive the ſinnes we have committed ſince the time that his Iudgements have beene upon the Land.</hi> Let it be the marke of the beaſt, and the badge of the Kingdome of Anti-Chriſt, when the Angell hath poured out the viall of wrath upon them, <hi>to gnaw their tongues for paine and blaſpheme the God of heaven becauſe of their ſores and torments, and not to repent of their evill deeds, Rev.</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:111960:19"/>16.10. But let us whom God hath yet reprived from the two deaths of warre and ſickneſſe which have beene ſo long upon the Kingdome, <hi>be on the mountaines like doves of the valleys, every one mourning for his own iniquity. Ezek.</hi> 7.16. I have now di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatcht the three queſtions, and have done with the doctrinall part; Let your patience I beſeech you hold out a little longer, while I cloſe up all with a ſeaſonable application.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place, the Text riſeth with full force againſt the moſt of us, I feare there are very few that can waſh our hands of the guilt of this ſinne, which ſtands here charged againſt the Jewes, <hi>They are not humbled even unto this day.</hi> We find by wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full experience that <hi>this day</hi> (to make uſe of our Saviours words, <hi>this Scripture is fullfilled in our eares.</hi> Though the wrath of God be in a high meaſure upon us, and hath long continued upon the Land: Yet where are the <hi>Jeremie's</hi> that mourne, the <hi>Daniel's</hi> that faſt, the <hi>Nehemiah's</hi> and <hi>Ezra'es</hi> that pray? the <hi>Preiſts</hi> that weepe betweene the Porch and the Altar, and ſay, <hi>Spare thy people O Lord?</hi> the <hi>Moſeſes</hi> that by the humiliation of themſelvs labour to <hi>ſtand in the gap?</hi> If there be but one <hi>houſe</hi> on fire in the Towne, there's a generall cry and running to helpe, every one carryes water to quench it: Now that the whole <hi>Kingdome</hi> is all on a Flame, and that cryes to every one of us, <hi>Water, water;</hi> ôh for ſome ſuch water as the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> poured out before the Lord in <hi>Mizpeh,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.6. <hi>faſting and crying out mightily, we have ſinned!</hi> ôh for buckets of teares, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent teares to quench a flaming Kingdome! ôh that every head were full, and every heart a Fountaine of thoſe waters, that we might draw thence to extinguiſh the devouring fire of Gods wrath; but alas woe is me! woe is this whole Nation e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one brings fuell to increaſe the flame, few or none labour to quench it. I know all that have any ſenſe of our preſent mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, cannot but reſent it with greife; doe ye not obſerve a deluge of ſinne upon the Kingdome, as well as a floud of wrath, which hath broken downe all the bankes of the feare of God
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:111960:19"/>and the reverence of man? <hi>Salvian</hi> complaines, <hi>in lib.</hi> 6. of the City <hi>Triers, Aſſiduitas calamitatum illic, augmentum criminum fait, iis ipſis quibus coërcebantur ſcelera plagis ereſcebant, ut putares poenam ipſorum criminum quaſi matrem eſſe vitiorum.</hi> I would our practice did not make it ſpeake <hi>Engliſh.</hi> Could you ever have thought impiety ſhould have riſen to ſo prodigious an height? is there any wickedneſſe dares not ſhew it ſelfe in publicke: <hi>The Licentious</hi> leudneſſe of uncleane perſons which heretofore abhorred the Light, (feare and ſhame made them put on a vaile then) now dares the day: all rapine and ſpoile and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence legitimated under the name of <hi>Plundering,</hi> the worſt kind of <hi>Robbery.</hi> Oppreſſion and unjuſt dealing improv'd by all the Art deceit can invent, as if all <hi>Conſcience</hi> as well as <hi>Lawes</hi> were aſleepe, if not quite dead. <hi>Heart-burnings and malice in every Towne and village, triumphing even over our common miſeries, as if nothing could reconcile us but onely utter ruine and the grave.</hi> It was the obſervation of <hi>Auguſtus Caſar, Conviviorum &amp; veſtium luxus agrotantis &amp; labentis imperii ſigna eſſe &amp; praenuncia. That exceſſe and riot in diet and apparell was a ſigne and forerunner of a languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and expiring Kingdome.</hi> Was ever nation more guilty of theſe two ſinnes, then ours <hi>of late?</hi> nay doe we abate now that God calls us to faſting and ſackcloath? Are not our Tables as full as heretofore? if not, are not our Tavernes and Ale-houſes ſo, thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>watry places,</hi> where (as <hi>Evagrius</hi> was wont to ſay) the <hi>Devill</hi> moſt of all delighteth to haunt? It is methinkes a very ſad ſtory which <hi>Salvian</hi> tells us of <hi>Carthage,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Alii foris jugulaban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, alii in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabantur. l. <hi>6.</hi> degub.</note> at a time when warre was even at their City Gates. That while the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my acted the <hi>Butchers</hi> upon their brethren without, they play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>Beaſts</hi> in uncleaneneſſe within; both Captives at the ſame time, they to the Barbarians, theſe to their Luſts; theſe revelling in the City, while they were groaning out their laſt in the Feild; theſe wallowing in their filth, while they lay weltring in their owne bloud: their caſe was much like ours; I would our courſe were not ſo like theirs. Was there ever a
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:111960:20"/>greater riot in Cloathes among all ſorts of people then now?<note place="margin">Ez. k. 16.51.</note> 
               <hi>England</hi> as well as <hi>Judah</hi> may ſeeme in her <hi>pride</hi> to juſtify <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom:</hi> a ſinne committed with an high hand as it were in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and deſpight of heaven: Caſt your eyes about you and ſee <hi>Nunquid hae Tunicae plangentium?</hi> Is this the habit and attire, this the garbe of mourners? Are not many arrayed as in the day of the Solemne Feaſt and triumph of the Church and Kingdome, rather then the time of the great perplexity and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe of both? the very names of our womens tackling would fill up the whole third Chapter of <hi>Eſay:</hi> Neither Gods Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, nor yet his Judgements can preach downe this ſinne, no not ſo much as their <hi>blacke ſpots</hi> and their <hi>paintings;</hi> Is it ſuch a <hi>blackenſſe</hi> as this thinke ye, that the Prophet <hi>Ioel</hi> ſpeakes of, <hi>Ioel</hi> 2.6. <hi>All faces ſhall gather blackeneſſe?</hi> Conſider that, and be affraid, ye know not how neare <hi>that day is,</hi> and remember the fate <hi>of painted</hi> Iezabell. Hath it not beene almoſt the Eccho of every Sermon againſt oathes and blaſphemies, and thoſe cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed imprecations? <hi>Oh doe not this abhominable thing that God bates;</hi> and indeed ſhould we be ſilent, the very <hi>ſtones</hi> in the ſtreetes would ſpeake; and the <hi>timber</hi> out of the houſe would anſwer them; yet the <hi>wicked know no ſhame,</hi> thoſe ſinnes are growne to a preſumption both againſt <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>King. The children of Iſrael,</hi> faith God, <hi>could not ſtand, but turned their backe before their enemies becauſe they were accurſed, Joſ.</hi> 7.12. Alas! then how ſhall theſe ſtand in the day of battaile, that doe ſo often curſe and confound themſelves? It is ſaid of the <hi>Thracians,</hi> that when it thunders they ſhoot up their Arrowes as it were in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance againſt heaven, theſe men their oathes and execrations. That excellent Law we have againſt this ſinne hath beene ſtrengthened by two pious Proclamations of late; Oh that there were a like care and zeale in the execution. Honourable, and Beloved, let me in the name of God and in the behalfe of this poore Kingdome beſeech you, as the Father in the Goſpell ſometimes did our Saviour for his child poſſeſſed with an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:111960:20"/>ſpirit, <hi>If you can doe any thing have compaſsion on us and helpe us.</hi> I would I could ſay with our Prophet.<note place="margin">Mark. 9.12.</note> 
               <hi>Surely thoſe are poore and fooliſh, they know not the way of the Lord nor the Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of their God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 5.4, 5
.</note> 
               <hi>I will goe to the great men and ſpeake unto them for they have knowne the way of the Lord and the Iudgement of their God.</hi> Oh ye heads of our Tribes,<note place="margin">2 Chron. 28.10.</note> and ye the ſonnes of <hi>Levi,</hi> as the Prophet <hi>Oded</hi> ſometimes ſpake, <hi>are there not with you, even with you, ſinnes againſt the Lord your God?</hi> Pardon me, I beſeech you if I ſpeake freely; The Sacrifice of this day is a <hi>ſinne offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,</hi> and 'tis Gods expreſſe command, <hi>Lev.</hi> 5.11. that neither <hi>oyle nor frankincenſe</hi> be put upon it, it is a <hi>ſinne offering.</hi> Lay your hand upon your heart, and tell me, what <hi>Reformation</hi> doe you find every one in his owne heart? what one ſinne have you forſaken of which before you were guilty? what one duty doe you now make conſcience of which you formerly neglected? doe you find a Frame of ſpirit in your ſelves anſwering the ſad and trembling condition of the Land? in a word, <hi>are ye humbled even unto this day?</hi> I would I could heare a good anſwer from you, that I might yet hope for better times; as your perſons are <hi>repreſentative,</hi> ſo are your ſinnes too; your ſinnes are the ſinnes of a whole <hi>Towne,</hi> a <hi>County,</hi> a <hi>Dioceſſe,</hi> and ſo ſhould I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count your humiliation. I doubt not but here are many which are exil'd from their houſes, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ifled of their Eſtates; your condition is ſad, but let me put the Queſtion to you; <hi>Are your hearts humbled?</hi> O <hi>Humiliation, Humiliation,</hi> what's be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of thee? where ſhall I finde thee that thou mayſt be a <hi>Pella, a City of refuge,</hi> to protect us from the Avengers of bloud; a <hi>Noahs Arke</hi> to ſave a ſinfull nation from the flood of Gods wrath? The <hi>City</hi> ſays, ſhe knowes thee not, the <hi>Court</hi> complaines thou art a ſtranger there, and the <hi>Country</hi> cries thou art gone out of the Land. Though the two great deſtroyers, the <hi>Red</hi> &amp; the <hi>Pale horſes,</hi> have march't through the whole Land, multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of people every day ſwept away, the cries of our oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, wounded, ſpoyled, undone freinds, Fathers, Brothers, kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:111960:21"/>ſound every houre in our eares, the ſighes, and teares, and groanes of our dying nation, are freſh, and loud; the ruine of the Kingdome, and deſolation as it were in ſight, yet are not moſt of us like that ſtupid judge in the <hi>Acts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 11.17</note> 
               <hi>And Gallio cared for none of theſe things?</hi> The truth is, when theſe cloudes firſt began to gather together, there was much perplexity amongſt us where the tempeſt then hanging over our heades would fall, we were all in great feare what the event of thoſe diſtractions would be; but now that our feares <hi>are come upon us,</hi> we ceaſe to be affraid; like thoſe <hi>Froggs</hi> in the Fable, when <hi>Jupiter</hi> threw downe the logg amongſt them, it put them in a great fright for a time, ſo that they held their croaking, but after a while, when the feare was a little over, they came neare to the Log and leapt upon it. The moſt of us ſeeme to be ſicke of <hi>Ichorams</hi> diſeaſe,<note place="margin">2 Chron. 21.15.</note> our <hi>bowells</hi> of compaſſion to others, (nay which is yet more) of pitty to our ſelves, <hi>are fallen out.</hi> We relent not at the murther and undoing of ſo many thouſands of our brethren; we can heare the <hi>paſsing-bell tole,</hi> and ſee the panges of death upon our owne Country with dry eyes and unhumbled hearts, and not ſo much as ſay, <hi>Alas my mother<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> what Jeremy, nay what ſeas of teares, even teares of blood, are ſufficient to lament this obſtinacy?<note place="margin">Jonah. 4.11.</note> 
               <hi>Should I not have compaſsion on a great City, wherein are ſix hundred thouſand ſoules that know not the right hand from the left?</hi> the greatneſſe of the multitude was a motive that prevailed with God to ſpare <hi>Ninive;</hi> and ſhould not this be an Argument as prevalent with us, to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw us from ſinne, and to perſwade us this day every one to humble himſelfe?<note place="margin">Exod. 10.3</note> O my wretched heart! <hi>How long Pharaoh like, wilt thou refuſe to humble thy ſelfe?</hi> If thou haſt no pitty up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thy ſelfe, yet ſhouldſt thou not have compaſſion upon a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing Kingdome? Shall I carry to my grave, nay to Hell with me the guilt of the bloud of ſo many thouſand Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents? Thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, men that walke in their ſleepe, they will venture upon dangerous precipices, becauſe they know
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:111960:21"/>not their danger, but when they are awakened, and come to ſee what they have done, they are aſtoniſh't, and even ſtrooke dead with the apprehenſion of the danger eſcaped, it is a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to ſee that men awakened by the loud cries of Gods judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments (or if we be aſleepe ſtill, we are in a dead ſleepe) ſhould dare to go on in ſuch deſperate wayes, as many of us do: that we ſhould have our eyes open and ſee our danger, and yet not be affraid, that the wrath of God ſhould be ſo long upon the Land, and we not <hi>humbled even unto this day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, to cloſe up all (I have already tyred both you and my ſelfe) as Jotham ſometime ſpake to the men of <hi>She-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jndg. 9.7.</note> 
               <hi>Hearken I beſeech you unto me, that the Lord may hearken un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you;</hi> I know the deſire of your ſoule is to doe good to your poore Country; your hearts cannot but yearne towards your diſtreſſed mother, and I hope with many of you, as this is the time of Jacobs trouble, ſo 'tis <hi>of Iacobs wreſtling</hi> too,<note place="margin">Hos. 12.4.</note> by ſtrong cries and teares, that the Lord would turne away from his fierce wrath, compoſe our bloudy diſtractions, and heale our Land. Do you deſire that God ſhould heare you? Why then hearken unto him,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>Humble your ſelves under the mighty hand of God,</hi> (he will heare the <hi>prayer of the humble</hi>) and what ever our preſent condition be, <hi>he will exalt us in due time;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 10.17.</note> if your owne hearts tell you that you have not beene humbled even unto this day, why then write the name of this day, let your hearts be humbled before the Lord this day: God forbid that any one of us ſhould carry an unhumbled heart out of this houſe of mourning: but when we are gone hence, let us enter every one into his owne Cloſet, and there powre out his affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted ſoule in ſighes, and groanes, and teares, and prayers, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord for his owne ſinnes and the ſinnes of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Oh let us make this day a day of Attonement for our ſelves, and this whole nation. When <hi>Benhadad</hi> was quite van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh't By <hi>Ahab,</hi> he ſent his ſervants with ſackcloth upon their loynes and ropes upon their necks, which came to the <hi>King of Iſrael,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>Thy ſervant Benhadad ſaith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kign. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.32.</note> 
               <hi>I pray
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:111960:22"/>thee let me live;</hi> the incouragement they had to do this, was becauſe they heard, the <hi>Kings of Iſrael were mercifull Kings.</hi> Let us do ſo this day, humble our ſelves in faſting, and teares, and begg our lives, and the life of this poore Kingdome at Gods hands; he is a mercifull <hi>God;</hi> ſay unto him, <hi>This expiring Church and dying Kingdome ſay, we pray thee let us live.</hi> O let us not deferre any longer to humble our ſelves. <hi>I have heard of thee by</hi> the hearing of the <hi>care</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iob</hi>) but <hi>now mine eye ſeeth</hi> thee,<note place="margin">Job 42.5, 6.</note> wherefore <hi>I abhorr my ſelfe in duſt and aſhes.</hi> we have heard long ſince by the hearing of the <hi>care,</hi> what deſtructions God hath wrought upon the Earth, we have heard of the Deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and many other Cities, and Kingdomes, of old, and of Germany and Ireland of late (the report is ſtill bleeding new,) Oh diſtreſſed Ireland! and happy had we beene had their examples awaked us, that we our ſelves might not have beene made an Hiſtory to others; but now that we have ſeene <hi>him by the eye,</hi> in the way of his judgements, what will become of us, if we do not humble and abhorre our ſelves? It is ſayed <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.20. <hi>That though the third part of men were killed, yet the remnant that were not ſlaine by the plagues, repented not of the workes of their hands, neither repented they of their mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, nor of their ſorceries, nor of their fornications, nor of their thefts.</hi> O let it not be ſayd of us of this Nation, us of this place, that though the ſword and the ſickneſſe have slaine, ſhall I ſay a 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> part of the Kingdome? we know that many thouſands are already fallen in England; the ſword is not yet put up into the ſheath, nor the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion to deſtroy taken from the peſtilence: O let it not (I ſay) be ſayd of us, that are as yet ſpared from deſtruction, that we have not <hi>repented of the workes of our hands.</hi> much leſſe let that be verified of us, which is ſpoken of the <hi>Nations. Rev.</hi> 16.8, 9. <hi>That when the fourth Angel had poured out his viall upon the Sunn, and power was given him to ſcorch men with fire, the men were ſcorched with great heate, and blaſphemed the name of God which hath power over thoſe plagues; and they repented not to give him the glory.</hi> The deſtroying Angel hath poured
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:111960:22"/>out the viall of Gods wrath upon the <hi>Sun</hi> of our peace &amp; former proſperity: Through the anger of the Lord of Hoſts is the whole land darkened: the fire that is kindled in all our dwellings hath ſcorched ſome of our perſons, &amp; conſumed many of our eſtates; the Lord forbid that this great affliction ſhould enrage our ſpirits to blaſpheme the name of that God who hath power over thoſe plagues; or that this great ſin ſhould be laid to the charge of the inhabitants of this Kingdome, that notwithſtanding all the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon them, <hi>yet they repented not to give God the glory.</hi> But let us rather make them our patternes, who are propounded to us as examples of repentance in times of diſtreſſe, <hi>and wreſtle with God</hi> this day by unfained contrition, for that <hi>bleſſing,</hi> which we cannot obtaine at the <hi>hands of men.</hi> Oh what would many of us give, (had we it to give) for that bleſſing which lately was as a <hi>price in the hand of fooles!</hi> Now what more doth God require of us for the redemption of this ineſtimable Pearle, but onely this, that we ſhould <hi>humble our ſelves?</hi> Honourable, and Beloved, there have beene many hopefull wayes taken for the recovery of our loſt Peace: your endeavours have expreſt your hearty deſires, to compoſe our unnaturall diviſions by an happy accommodation: the Royall tongue hath prevented me in the acknowledgement of your paines this way; the Lord reward it unto you, and all thoſe that are thus minded, and the bleſſing of the Peace-makers ever reſt upon you. But the many and great ſinnes of this Nation have blaſted the ſucceſſe, and as yet hid theſe good things from us. What remaines now, but that Ye and We, and all of us by unceſſant prayers and teares importune the throne of grace, and humble our ſelves before the <hi>God of peace,</hi> for the <hi>bleſsing of peace?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh, but methinkes I heare ſome ſay, Alas my heart, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all that hath beene ſaid, is yet hard and unhumbled: Can you give me ſome receit, that may break it and melt it into teares of Repentance?</p>
            <p>Take this breiſe preſcription, and carry it home along with thee: in the firſt place,<note place="margin">Zech. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.10</note> pray to God that he would <hi>poure out upon thee the ſpirit of grace and ſupplication.</hi> Begge a looke from Chriſt,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:111960:23"/>there is a vertue in Chriſt his looke to peirce the hardeſt heart,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke 22.61, 62.</hi> Reſpice Domine Ieſu, ut ſciamus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lere deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe. Pſal. 147.18. Ioſ. 15.19.</hi>
               </note> and to ſoften it into godly ſorrow and remorſe for it's ſinnes. Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus looked backe, and <hi>Peter</hi> went out, and wept bitterly. The foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of penitent teares is in heaven; our hearts are naturally dry, like the deſarts of <hi>Arabia,</hi> untill he that <hi>turnes the wilderneſſe into a ſtanding poole, and the dry ground into ſprings of waters,</hi> cauſeth his ſpirit to <hi>blow</hi> up on them, and then <hi>the waters ſhall flow.</hi> Goe to God with that requeſt which <hi>Achſa</hi> did to her Father, <hi>Give me</hi> O Lord, <hi>the ſprings of water, the upper and the nether ſprings,</hi> that I may weep for our diſtreſſe, but more for our ſinnes. In the next place, raiſe up thy ſoule upon the wings of heavenly meditation, and fly up to Mount <hi>Golgotha,</hi> and there looke upon him whom thou haſt peir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. Conſider him in his bitter agony, ſweating drops of bloud trickling downe to the ground: In thoſe conſternations of ſpirit, trembling under the unſupportable burden of his Fathers wrath; hanging upon the Croſſe, nail'd hands and feet; forſaken of men, and in his owne ſenſe of God too, breathing out his afflicted ſoule in a loud cry. And then reflect upon thy ſelfe, not onely as the Author of all,<note place="margin">Heb. 6.6.</note> but alſo as one that by thy knowne, wilful, preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuous ſinnes haſt often <hi>crucified him afreſh, and put him to an open ſhame. The fountaine of bloud</hi> opened in Chriſts ſide for the expia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſinne, will open <hi>a fountaine of teares</hi> in thy heart for the commiſſion of it. <hi>They ſhall looke upon him whom they have peirced, and they ſhall mourne for him, as one mournes for his onely ſonne, and ſhall be in bitterneſſe for him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zech. 22.10.</note> 
               <hi>as one is in bitterneſſe for his firſt borne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the Lord in mercy bring home and ſettle that which hath beene ſpoken at this time, upon every one of our hearts. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
